<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Nathan Mugerwa]]></title><description><![CDATA[Nathan Mugerwa's personal website.]]></description><link>https://gatsby-starter-blog-demo.netlify.app</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 05:10:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[2021 Plans | Bet Maker]]></title><description><![CDATA[When I was in high school I traded stocks. I would trade in between gulps of chocolate milk at the lunch table, before physics quizzes and…]]></description><link>https://gatsby-starter-blog-demo.netlify.app/bet-maker/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://gatsby-starter-blog-demo.netlify.app/bet-maker/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When I was in high school I traded stocks. I would trade in between gulps of chocolate milk at the lunch table, before physics quizzes and orchestra rehearsals — fucking everywhere. I was a fiend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I learned countless lessons from my time as a trader that’ll stick with me for the rest of my life. Many of these lessons guided my decision to take this year off from university, and we’ll go through them below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Each decision you make is a bet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every single decision you make is a bet based on some known or hidden statistical process. Crossing the street without looking both ways, taking a job, choosing whom to marry, and deciding whether to take time off or return to school during a pandemic; these are all bets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don’t explicitly think in these terms for huge “life decisions” like choosing who I wanna marry or choosing a new career path; to me, that would be a bit too dispassionate. Plus, I think intuition works surprisingly well in these situations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for most other decisions I go in the other direction. And for my 2021 plan, I chose to explicitly bet on the statistical processes of COVID-19 and job interviewing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choose the bet with maximal expectation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expectation/expected value is an idea central to statistics. Intuitively, it answers the question: “How much should I expect to gain from making a bet in this scenario?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m using Expectation in a very intuitive, non-rigorous way below. I apologize to my math people 💗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the hood, we weigh how much we stand to gain from each particular outcome by how likely that outcome is, then sum up all of these weighings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my situation it was roughly this:
(probability of getting internships) * (value of getting internships) + (probability of not getting internships) * (value of not getting internships and returning to school)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Breaking down the left-hand-side of the equation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probability of me getting internships was unusually high because of the unhealthy amounts of prep I did over the summer (~10 hours every day). And the value of getting those internships was again unusually high: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would gain an incredible edge in the job market, just as the pandemic had made job-hunting significantly more competitive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would be able to pay off my student loans and build a rainy day fund, just as pandemic-induced economic uncertainty had made having a solid financial foundation paramount.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would not have to attend Zoom University Inc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Breaking down the right-hand-side of the equation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probability of me not getting an internship was very low and the value that I’d be losing was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would graduate a year early.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s literally it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not losing out on the college experience™, nor a high-quality education, nor extracurriculars, nor literally anything else that in a normal year would be the value of spending that year in school. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ain’t a difficult decision, mayne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Buy into blood, sell into exuberance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After being sent home from campus in March, I immediately started planning to take a gap year. This was because I immediately recognized that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pandemic had actually strengthened the industries that I’m interested in, making it very feasible to find work during a gap year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The expected value of taking a gap year had gotten wildly larger due to the decreased value of an online education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reasoning is similar to why times of chaos tend to reveal incredible opportunities in the financial markets .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;When fortune is in your favor, place bets more aggressively&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In trading, the strength of a strategy changes over time. This is why traders are always staring at 30 fucking monitors. They’re gleaning information in order to update their view on how strong their strategies are. And when they discern their strategies are in a stronger position, they deploy more capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thinking underlies one of my motivations for taking four internships in a row rather than one, two or three. When I was applying, I had spent ~10 hours a day studying algorithms for the previous 3 months. This meant that, at that moment, the probability of me passing any technical interview was highest — fortune was in my favor. And so I applied to every interesting/difficult-to-get-into company I could think of and ended up getting offers with a +90% success rate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You cannot live a fulfilling, maximized life while staying on the well-charted path&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a personal belief of mine; I can’t prove it to be true. But I’ve arrived at it through looking at the lives of everyone I admire: from revolutionary leaders to civil rights icons to pioneers of technology, not a single one of them evolved into the people they did through taking the well-charted path. I hope that this year will be one of those “uncharted paths” times in my life, where I maximize growth through removing myself from the charted road of a four-year education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So long as your process is solid and you can see (through quantitative measures) that you’re improving, do not give up on the goal you’re reaching towards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The headline says it all. And I don’t mean to sound like a fucking high school basketball coach but I genuinely believe in trusting the process. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous recruiting cycle, I went 0/+300 applications. I bombed almost every technical interview I did, failed every final round, and was ghosted by hundreds of companies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember getting on the plane to leave Seattle after interviewing with Microsoft, feeling confident I had finally broken through. I glanced at my e-mail and saw that they had sent my results: “Unfortunately, we won’t be moving forward with an offer at this time…“. I could barely breath and had to fight back tears (mostly so that the flight attendents wouldn’t think I was about to bug out on some domestic terrorist shit). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But genuinely, that shit hurt so bad. I had sacrificed so much of my free-time, mental health, social life and even physical health for this process and had ended up with absolutely no results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;But I didn’t give up because I knew that I was progressing at a rate that guaranteed eventual success&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kept an Excel sheet where I tracked all of my weaknesses, how many hours I was working, how efficient those hours were, and my general interview performance. At the end of that cycle I had zero offers. But this Excel sheet showed unwavering growth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the beginning, I could not pass first round interviews. Towards the end, I was consistently making it to 2nd rounds and even final rounds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of unique, high-relevance problems I had done was growing across all areas (i.e. Tree problems, graph problems, binary search problems, …). My weaknesses were getting slimmer every day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bottom-line: I was getting better at a pace that would allow me to be extremely prepared for the next cycle, should I keep preparing; and I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You made it to the end!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proud of you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I’m not sure how this site will evolve. I’ll probably spruce it up cause it’s bare atm. But this section will stay the same: me having streams of consciousness about random shit. Hopefully some of it will be useful to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>